[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi, I'm Adam Porter, and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
Today we're going to talk about the
Android development enviroment.
An integrated set of tools to help you
create your own Android applications.
In our last lesson, I introduced you to
the Android platform itself.
I talked about how the Android platform is
a software stack
for building and running mobile
applications.
And if you've used an Android device, to
write email, to take photos, to get
directions, to play games and so on,
then you've seen the Android platform in
action.
And you have a good idea about what it can
do.
So, the next question then, is how do we
use the Android platform to write our own
Android apps?
Well, one part of the answer, is that you
need to learn
the details of the Android platform
itself.
And we'll do that throughout this class.
Another part of the answer, though, is
that you need to learn and
master the tools that will allow you to
make use of the platform.
In order to create those new applications.
And that's what we're going to focus on
today.
Now the tools that I'm talking about are
called the Android development
environment, and you should think of them
as your workbench for creating
Android applications, and like any skilled
craftsperson, the more comfortable you are
with your tools, the easier it's going to
be to produce top quality work.
Now in this lesson, we'll cover several
topics.
First, I'll explain how you can set up
your development environment including
installing the Android SDK, the Eclipse
integrated development environment or IDE,
and
the Android developer tools.
Then I'll show you the Eclipse IDE in
action.
And we'll create a very simple Android
application.
After that, I'll show you some specific
tools; such as, the Android
emulator which allows you to run
Android applications without needing a
physical device.
And then I'll show you how to use the
eclipse
debugger to help you diagnose any eventual
problems that you might
have in your application.
And lastly, I'll show you a variety of
other
tools designed to help you further perfect
your applications.
And before you get started make sure that
you have a supported operating system.
For Windows, these include Windows XP,
Windows Vista, and Windows 7.
For Mac you'll need Mac OS X 10, 10.5.8 or
later.
Running on an Intel-based CPU.
Several Linux distributions will work as
well.
Please see the Android developers' website
for more information.
Now, you should also make sure that you
have
the Java Development Kit Version six, or
the JDK6 installed.
And be aware that JDK6 is not the latest
version of Java, so
some of you may have version seven, but
that's not fully supported by Android.
Again, check the following website for
more information.
So now we're ready to get started.
So first download and install the Android
Developer Tools or ADT Bundle.
Now I suggest you do this right now and
that way you can
follow along with my examples while you
watch the rest of this lesson.
You can find the ADT Bundle at the URL
shown here.
Now I'll also point out that Google has
recently released a new IDE, called
Android Studio,
which they expect will ultimately become
the preferred IDE for doing Android
development.
However, since Android Studio is still
currently in a preview or
pre-released state, I'm going to do my
demonstrations for this class using
Eclipse.
But you're free to, to use Eclipse or to
use Android Studio, as you wish.
Now, the ADT Bundle provides you with
several things.
First, it has the latest
Android platform including the latest
libraries, reusable software, tools, and
documentation.
It also includes the eclipse IDE and
Android specific plugins.
It has additional tools that support
developing, running, testing,
and debugging your Android apps and it has
the latest
system image for the emulator so that you
can
run and debug your Android applications
without needing to have
an actual device.
In our last lesson we talked about the
Android platform.
So, today we'll talk about the other three
elements, one by one.
But before we do that, let's look at
a very simple Android application called,
Hello Android.
And I'll be referring back to this
application throughout the lesson.
Now
here I'm showing my phone's home screen.
First, I'll click on the launch here icon.
And then I'll click on the Hello Android
icon to launch
the application, the application starts,
and displays the words, Hello world.
Now that's about as simple as it gets, but
let's walk through the process of writing
the Hello Android application, using the
eclipse IDE.
Now this is the Eclipse IDE opened to full
screen.
Let's start by creating a new Android
application project.
Now one way to do that is to go to
the File menu, then New, and then select
Android Application Project.
Once you do this, you'll see a series of
dialogue boxes that ask you for
information about this application.
On the first screen enter
Hello Android, all one word for the
application name, and for the project
name.
Where it asks for the package name, I'm
using
course.examples.helloandroid but you could
use something else if you'd like.
Now go ahead and leave the other boxes
alone, and hit Next.
Now for this exercise, let's just click
through the next few screens.
They control application
characteristics that we haven't discussed
yet, but we'll
come back to them when time is right.
Once you arrive at the screen titled,
Blank
Activity, go ahead and hit the Finish
button.
Eclipse will generate the application's
source code and layout files.
And once it's finished, you will open a
file called activity_main.xml.
This file defines
the application's user interface layout.
And based on this file, Eclipse
will show you whatever it can about how
this application will look when it runs.
As you can see here, Hello Android will
display a simple screen with the words,
hello world.
Let's also take a quick look at the source
code for this application.
Let's open up the file main activity.java.
Now that opens up an editor window,
showing the contents of the file.
And I won't talk too much about the source
code right now, except
to say that when this application runs;
the on create method of this
class will be called and that code will
set up and display the
application's user interface screen, so
let's run this code to see what happens.
One way of running an application
is to, click on the project in the File
pane, then select Run As, and then select
Android Application.
Now a dialogue box pops up, asking where
to run the application?
In this case, I only have my phone
connected, so I'll choose that.
And now, we wait while the application is
copied to the phone, and then run.
And there you have it.
Your first Android application, running on
a real device.
Now, the phone I use is the Nexus Four.
Let's suppose I'd like to test this out on
a different phone.
Let's say the Galaxy Nexus but I don't
have one of those phones.
In that case rather than run out and buy a
Galaxy
Nexus, I can run Hello Android on an
emulated Galaxy Nexus
using the Android Emulator.
And in order to do that, I first need to
create the emulated phone instance that
I'll use inside the emulator.
Now these emulated phone instances are
called virtual devices.
Let's go back to the clips, and set
up a virtual device corresponding to a
Galaxy Nexus.
So now we're back in Eclipse.
First, I'll go up to the tool bar, and
launch the Android virtual device manager,
it might be a bit hard
to see here, but look for the icon, that
shows an android in a box.
Clicking that will display a dialogue box
showing existing
virtual devices and allowing you to make
new ones.
Let's click on the New button
which will bring up another dialogue box.
Under AVD name or Android Virtual Device
name you can give this virtual device any
name you want.
Now go to the Device pull down menu and
select Galaxy Nexus, that will
fill in a bunch of information for you
such as the target platform to use.
In this case let's
use Android 4.2.2.
I'm going to add some memory to the SD
card just in case we may need it later.
And then I'll hit okay.
You can see the virtual device you just
created.
Click on that and then click Start.
Now go ahead and click through to the next
screen.
And then we'll need to wait several
minutes while the virtual device boots up.
I'll come back later when it's done.
Okay, we're almost there, just a few
seconds more.
And there's the home screen of an emulated
Galaxy Nexus.
Now that the Galaxy Nexus is running,
let's return to Eclipse.
And this time, I'll install and run hello
android
on the emulated phone rather than on a
physical device.
So just like we did before, let's click on
the project name.
Select Run As, and then
select Android application.
A dialogue box up, box
pops up, showing us connected devices.
And this time, instead of selecting an
actual device, select the virtual device
that you just started and click okay.
Eclipse will install the application on
the virtual device and then run it.
And here you go, Hello Android, running on
the emulator.
Today I've shown you that you can build
applications like
Hello Android on an actual device, inside
an emulator or both.
And there are pluses and minuses with each
of these
approaches; for example, the benefits of
using an emulator include;
that the emulator is cheaper, you don't
have to buy
all the devices that you may want to test
on.
Also, unlike the phone, the emulator
allows you to easily configure hardware
characteristics,
like the size of the sd card, the display
size, whether the device has a trackball,
and so on.
Also, many modifications that you make or
any of the modifications that you make.
Are isolated to this emulated device, so
you don't have to worry
that your testing will mess up your phone
or its data or configuration.
Now on the other hand, emulators have some
downsides as well.
For example, the Android Emulator is
pretty slow and
that can be frustrating when you're trying
to rapidly experiment
and tune your app and you have to wait for
the emulator to start up and run and shut
down.
Also some features are not well supported
by the emulator.
For instance, there is no support for
bluetooth connectivity and no
support for connecting accessories to the
emulator via a USB cable.
Also, some software
features aren't available at by default in
the
emulator, so certain applications won't
run on it.
And finally, at the end of the day, the
emulator is not a device.
You can't know how your application is
going to look and perform
on an actual device just by seeing it on
an emulator.
Let's take a look at some of the advanced
features that the emulator supports.
For instance, you can configure the
emulator to
emulate the speed and latency of different
cellular networks.
You can configure the emulator to emulate
different battery states, such as
whether you're running low on battery
power, or currently charging the device.
You can also inject mock location
coordinates to
make testing of location or applications
much easier.
And typically, these features help to test
code that
must respond to environment events.
For instance, applications are often
designed to
do different things, depending on the
battery level.
Let me show you how easy this is.
Here I'm showing a terminal window.
And an emulator running on a virtual
device.
In the terminal window, I'll use telnet to
connect to the emulator.
You can see port number on which the
emulator's listening in that
emulator's window title bar.
And in this case that's 5554.
So I'll type telnet local host 5554.
Now I'll set
the network charactersitics to emulate a
slower edge network.
I'll type network, speed, edge.
And notice that the cellular network
status
icon in the notification bar has now
changed.
Now I'll change it back to 3G network
speed.
And now I'll change the battery status to
reflect
a phone that is running out of battery
power.
I'll type in power, capacity 5.
And again you can see that the battery
status indicator in
the notification bar is changed to reflect
the lower battery level.
Now I'll change the charging status to
indicate that the phone is not plugged in.
I'll type power status
not charging.
And again as you can see the
battery status indicator no longer shows a
lightning
bolt, and has changed color to indicate
that
the device is almost completely out of
power.
Also if I open the maps application you
can see
that the emulator thinks that I'm
currently somewhere near Washington DC.
However, I can change that by inputting a
new set of location coordinates like so,
geo fix 0.00 40.00 and as you can see
the maps application now shows that I've
been
transported somewhere near a beach in
sunny Spain.
The An, the
Android emulator also allows you to
emulate network interactions
such as receiving a phone call or a SMS
message.
Back in the terminal window, I'll
reconnect to the emulator over telnet.
And then, I'll give the emulator a command
which will cause it to emulate an incoming
SMS message.
That command is sms send followed by the
sender's phone number, 3015555555.
And then the text message.
In this case, this is
a text message.
Now, keep your eye on the emulator window
to see what happens when I hit Return.
And as you can see, the emulator's
notification
bar now contains a notification,
indicating that the
emulated phone just received the SMS
message and
we can pull down on the notification bar.
And then start messaging application to
get a closer look at that SMS message.
Android also allows two emulators to
interact with each other.
Here I'm showing two emulator instances
running, in one
I'll open the phone application and start
to dial the number of
the second.
The number of the second
emulator is the port number shown at the
top of that emulator.
In this case, 5554.
Now you can see that the second
emulator has received the call.
And is ringing its user.
So I'll pick up the incoming call in the
second emulator, and as you can see, now
the first emulator's interface has changed
to reflect that the call is connected.
Now, if one of the parties hits the Hold
button,
that will also be reflected in both phone
applications.
And once the users are done with the call,
I can hang up
one of the emulators and both emulators
show that the call has been disconnected.
And of course that' just a few of the many
things that you can do with the emulator.
There are many, many other interesting
features as well and if you want to know
more I would recommend that you take a
look at the emulator page, on an,
on the Android developer's website.