Hi, I'm Adam Porter, and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
Today I am going to introduce you to the
Android platform.
I'll start by giving you an overview of
the
Android platform, and the components that
make it up.
And then I'll present each of these
components and
discuss how they help developers build
great mobile applications.
So let's get started.
The Android platform is a software stack.
And it was designed primarily, but not
exclusively, to support mobile devices
such as phones and tablets.
And this stack has several layers going
all the
way from low level operating system
services that manage
the device itself up to sample
applications, things like
the phone dialer, the context database,
and a web browser.
Android also comes with a software
developers kit,
or STK, which is used to create Android
applications.
And finally there's tons of documentation,
tutorials, blogs, and examples
that you can use to improve your own
understanding of Android.
And I encourage you to take advantage of
all of these resources.
Now this graphic represents the Android
software stack and
as you can see it's organized into several
layers.
At the bottom, there is a Linux kernel
layer.
Above that, there are system libraries,
and the Android runtime system.
Above that, there's a rich application
framework
layer to support the development of new
applications.
And at the very top, Android provides some
standard applications.
Again things like the phone dialer, the
web browser, and contacts database.
So let's look at each of these layers
in detail, starting with the Linux Kernel
layer.
The Linux Kernel layer is the lowest layer
of software in the Android platform.
This layer provides the core services that
any Android computing device will rely on.
Android's Linux kernel, just like any
Linux kernel, provides generic operating
system services.
For example, it provides a permissions
architecture, so that
you can restrict access to data and
resources to
only those processes that have the proper
authorizations.
It supports memory and process management,
so that multiple
processes can run simultaneously without
interfering with each other.
It handles low level details of file, and
network IO.
And it also allows device drivers to be
plugged in, so that
Android can communicate with a wide range
of low-level hardware components that
are often coupled to computing devices.
Things like memory, and radios, and
cameras.
In addition to the common services
supported by any
Linux kernel, Android's Linux kernel
also includes several Android-specific
components.
For example, Android's Linux kernel
includes its own power
management services because mobile devices
often run on battery power.
It provides its own memory sharing, and
memory
managing features, because mobile devices
often have limited memory.
And Android Linux kernel also includes
its own interprocess communication
mechanism called the
binder, which allows multiple processes to
share data and services In sophisticated
ways.
And of course, this is just a few of the
Android-specific features.
There are many others as well.
Next layer up includes a variety of system
libraries.
These libraries are typically written in C
and C++ and for
that reason they are often referred to as
the native libraries.
And these native libraries handle a lot of
the core, performance sensitive activities
on your device.
Things like quickly rendering web pages
and updating the display.
For example, Android has its
own System C Library which implements the
standard OS system calls, which do
things like process and thread creation,
mathematical computations, memory
allocation, and much more.
There's the surface manager for updating
the display.
A media framework for playing back audio
and video files.
Webkit for rendering and displaying web
pages.
Open GL, for high
performance graphics, and SQLite, for
managing in memory relational databases.
In addition to the system libraries, this
layer also includes
the Android run time, which supports
writing and running Android applications.
And there are two components in the
Android run time that we'll talk about
today.
The core Java libraries and the Dalvik
Virtual Machine.
Let's talk about each of those one at a
time.
Now first, Android applications are
typically
written in the Java programming language.
And to make it easier to write
applications, Android provides a number of
reusable Java building blocks.
For instance, the Java and Java X or Java
Extensions packages include basic software
for things like common data structure,
concurrency mechanisms, and file IO.
The Android packages have software that's
specific
to the life cycle of mobile applications.
The org packages support various internet,
or web operations.
And the Junit packages support the unit
testing of applications.
The second part of the Android Runtime, is
the Dalvik Virtual Machine.
The Dalvik Virtual Machine is the software
that actually executes Android
applications.
Now, as I just told you,
Android applications are typically written
in Java.
So you might have assumed that since
they're written in
Java they would probably run on a standard
Java virtual machine.
But in fact, that's not the case.
What typically happens is that developers
first write their applications in the Java
programming language.
Then, a Java compiler will compile the
Java
source code files into multiple Java
bytecode files.
Next, a tool called DX transforms the Java
bytecodes into
a single file of a different bytecode
format called dex.
And this bytecode file is usually called
classes.dex.
Next, the dex file is packaged with
other application resources and installed
on the device.
And finally, when the user launches the
application, the
Dalvik virtual machine will then execute
the classes.dex file.
Now, the reason for doing all this is
that the Dalvik virtual machine, unlike
the Java
virtual machine, was specifically designed
to run in
the resource-constrained environment which
is typical of mobile devices.
And when I say resource-constrained, what
I
mean is that compared to a typical desktop
device, the typical mobile device is less
powerful and more limited in many ways.
For example, it will probably have a
slower
CPU, less memory, and a limited battery
life.
So, if you're interested in finding out
more
about the Dalvik Virtual Machine itself,
then I
recommend you take a look at this video,
Dalvik VM Internals, by Dan Bornstein of
Google.
The next layer in the Android software
stack is the application framework.
The application framework contains
reusable software that
many mobile applications are likely to
need.
For example, as we'll see in a
minute, the view system contains common
graphical elements.
Things like buttons and icons that
many applications include in their user
interfaces.
Let's take a deeper look at some of these
components.
One application framework component is the
package manager.
The package manager is essentially a
database that keeps
track of all the applications currently
installed on your device.
So here's the home screen of my phone.
When I click on the launcher icon, the
phone shows me a bunch
of icons, each one representing an
application package that's stored on my
phone.
The package manager stores information
about these applications.
And that's useful for several reasons.
For example, it allows applications to
find and contact each
other, so that one application can share
data with another application,
or so that one application can request
services from another.
Another application framework component is
the window manager.
The window manager, as the name suggests,
manages the many windows that comprise
applications.
Here I'm launching the browser
application, which appears as two windows.
At the top, there's the system
notification
bar, which displays various status
indicators that tell
the user about things like WiFi signal
strength, remaining battery power, and the
current time.
There's also a main application window
that in
this case is showing the current web page.
An application can also use various
sub-windows
such as when it shows menus or dialogues.
As I mentioned earlier, the application
framework also contains the view system.
The view system contains many common
graphical user interface elements.
Such as icons, text entry boxes, buttons,
and much more.
Let's take a look at the phone
application.
As you can see the phone application's top
level
user interface is organized as a set of
tabs.
And each tab corresponds to a different
user
interface that supports a different set of
tasks.
The phone tab shows me a phone dialer.
The call log tab shows a list of recent
incoming and outgoing calls.
And the contacts tab shows a list
of stored contacts.
Now as I just said, when I select the
phone tab,
I'm show, shown a user interface that
mimics a phone keypad.
That keypad is made up of view
system components, things like buttons and
text views.
And then the application will listen as I
press these buttons, and then respond by
writing the corresponding digits to a text
view to show me what number I'm dialing.
The next application
framework component is the resource
manager.
This component manages the non-compiled
resources that make up an application.
Things like strings, graphics, and user
interface layout files.
And to give you an example of non-compiled
resources, let's go back to the phone
application again.
Now this tab has
some English words on it.
And that's fine because I speak English.
But Android is available around the world.
It's not limited to English speakers, and
so it's important that
we have an easy way to customize
applications for other languages.
And one way that Android supports that is
that it lets you define strings in
multiple languages.
For example, the phone application has a
string file
for Italian words as well as one for
English words.
So if you speak Italian, then you can go
into the settings
application and select Italian as your
default language.
Now, if I go back and rerun
the phone application,
you'll see that Android
will use the appropriate
Italian words rather than
the English words.
And of course
you can do this for as many languages as
makes sense for your application.
Another application framework component is
the activity manager.
Now at a high level Android activities
often correspond to a single user
interface screen.
Applications are then created by stringing
together
multiple activities through which the user
can navigate.
The Activity Manager helps to coordinate
and support that kind of navigation.
So suppose I want to listen to
some music.
So here I'll click on the launcher icon to
show my applications.
From there, I can click on the music
player
icon and that will start an activity that
brings
up a user interface screen showing the
music I
have on my device, in this case sorted by
artist.
I can select an artist and see the albums
by that artist.
I can select one album by clicking on it.
And this starts another activity that
brings up another user
interface screen showing the songs in the
album I just selected.
Now if I hit the Back button, I can go
back to
the last activity and, for example, I can
choose a different album.
Now I can click on a specific song in that
album
and yet another activity starts up, that
brings up yet another
user interface screen, allowing me to play
this song.
Another application framework component
implements content providers.
Content providers are essentially
databases that allow
applications to store and share structured
information.
For example, here we see that the phone
application can access
stored contact information and use it to
dial a phone number.
And it can do that because the contact
information is
stored in a content provider.
And even better, content providers are
designed to work across applications.
So not only can the phone dialer use the
contact information, but
so can the MMSM, messaging application and
so can various social media applications.
Let's take a look.
So going back to the phone application, I
can
select the Contact tab to access stored
contact information.
I can select one of the contacts to
quickly dial that contact.
Now as I said, I can do that
because contact information is stored in a
content provider.
And again, even better, content providers
are designed to work across applications.
So not only can the phone dialer use the
contacts but so can
the MMS messaging application, and so can
Twitter,
Facebook, my email readers, and things
like that.
The next application framework component
is the location manager.
The location manager allows applications
to receive location and
movement information, such as that
generated by the GPS system.
And this allows applications to perform
context-specific tasks,
things like finding directions from the
current location.
Now here I'm calling up the Google
Maps application, which queries the
location manager for
my current location, and then shows a map
of the area around that current location.
The last application framework component
I'll
talk about today is the Notification
Manager.
The Notification Manager allows
applications to
place information in the Notification Bar.
For example, to let users know that
certain events have occurred.
For example, suppose I want to send my
wife an MMS message.
And let's suppose that right at this
minute, she's
writing an email or making a phone call or
whatever.
So although she probably wants to know
that I've sent her an
MMS message, she might not want that to
disrupt her right now.
Well, Android handles this with a
Notification Manager.
And the way that works is that there's
some software
running on her phone, that's always
listening for incoming MMS messages.
When one arrives, that software uses the
Notification Manager
to place an icon in her phone's
notification bar.
And that's shown here as a little smiley
face icon.
And I've whited out some of the, some of
the information there for privacy.
And when shes ready she can pull down on
the notification
bar which then shows more information
about the specific notification.
And if she clicks on that notification the
MMS application will
start up and she can read and hopefully
respond to my message.
The last layer of the Android software
stack is the Application layer.
As I said earlier, Android comes with some
built-in applications.
And these include things like the Home
Screen, the
Phone Dialer, the Web Browser, an Email
Reader, and more.
And one of the things that's really nice
about Android
is that none of these apps is hardcoded
into the system.
If you have a better app, you can
substitute your app for any of these
standard apps.
So that's all for the Android platform.
Please join me next time, when
we'll explore the Android Development
Environment.
See you then.