Hi I'm Adam Porter and this is Programming
Applications for Android Handheld Systems.
Eclipse comes with a debugger that gives
developers powerful
tools for examining the internal state of
a running application.
And this can be useful of course when you
have a
bug in your application and you're not
sure exactly what's causing it.
So lets use the Eclipse debugger
to examine an application.
Here I'm showing a simple Android
application.
That I've named The Answer.
This app is supposed to show you
the answer to life, the universe, and
everything.
Which, as The Hitchhiker's Guide to the
Universe tells us, is 42.
As you can see however, instead of
displaying
42, this app says, we may never know.
So, clearly, there's a bug in here
somewhere.
Let's use the debugger to track that bug
down.
So, here we are in Eclipse.
First, I'll open up the Answer application
and show you its source code.
Now, the truth is, that this is a pretty
silly program.
And the bug will be fairly obvious.
Once you've looked at the code.
But my goal here is to show you the
debugger, so just
between us, let's pretend that we don't
really know what the bug is.
Now you can see that there's an array
called answers.
Through which the program will search,
looking for the answer 42.
There's the on create method.
That is the starting point when the class
is executed.
Inside On Create there's a call to a
method called Find Answer.
And Find Answer is listed down below.
Now, Find Answer is supposed to search the
answers
array and return the number 42 if it's in
there, or minus one if it's not.
The program stores Find Answers return
value.
And then uses it to compute a string
called Output.
And then finally the program displays the
Output string.
So, since I don't know were the bug is,
I'll,
I decide to use the debugger to debug the
program.
And the first thing I'll do then
is to set a break point.
That stops the program when it enters the
Oncreate method.
Now instead of running the program, I'll
debug it by right clicking the project
name, selecting debug as, and then
selecting Android application.
I'll click okay.
And when the application reaches Oncreate,
it stops.
And shows me the debug view with the
current line highlighted
in the source code.
Now, at this point, I'll step through the
code line by line, examining the program
state.
I step forward, I select Step Over from
the tool bar, which advances the program
one line.
I'm now at the line that calls Find Answer
and stores the return result in the
variable val.
Once I step over this line, you will see
that
the value of the variable val is now minus
ten.
Which is already a problem.
It should have been 42.
So the problem is certainly down there in
the Find Answer method.
So let's look more closely at Find Answer.
And to do that, I'll put a break
point at Find Answer, and then restart the
application.
Now this time, when
the application
stops at On
Create.
I'll hit the Step Over button which will
let the
application continue executing until the
find answer break point is hit.
I can step forward in this method and
examine the values
of variables to determine that 42 is
indeed in the array.
And that Find Answer sees it but considers
it the wrong answer.
Anyway, as I'm sure you figured out long
ago,
the problem is that I'm accidentally
checking for not equals.
Rather than for equals equals.
So I'll fix that and start over, and this
time we'll see the correct behavior.
Now, just to make sure, let's go back and
fire up the answer.
And yes, the answer to the life, the
universe, and everything, is again 42.
Now I think debuggers help most when you
have a reasonably good idea of
where your problem is, so you can focus in
on a few lines of code.
But in many other situations that kind of
low level,
instruction by instruction examination
that debuggers are so good at supporting.
Is less helpful.
Instead it may be easier to use more
general tools
that instrument your system and let you
monitor its behavior as it runs over time.
Android provides a number of these
monitoring tools,
in its Dalvik Debug Monitor Service, or
DDMS.
Today I'll talk about four of these tools.
A File Explorer for viewing a device's
file system.
Logcat, for logging and displaying run
time events.
Traceview for displaying method execution
traces.
And Hierarchyview for examining user
interface layouts.
Let's look at these tools and see how you
access them from Eclipse.
[BLANK AUDIO] First,
let's open the DDMS perspective which
exposes a number of
panes and buttons who are accessing the
different DDMS tools.
We now see device pane that shows the
devices that are currently connected.
And shows a list of debuggable processes
running on these devices.
The first tool we'll look at is the File
Explorer.
This view shows, shows you the files on
your file system.
For example, here we see that this device
has a slash data, slash data directory.
In which applications can store their
persistent data.
This device also has an external memory
card.
And there's some directories there for
storing music and movies and other things.
The next pane I'll talk about shows the
Logcat view.
Android logs many events by default.
That is as the software runs, it spits
out information about the things that are
happening
on the device, and this information is
stored,
it can be displayed in the Logcat view.
Android also provides methods that
let developers log their own information.
Another DDMS tool is Traceview.
Traceview allows you to trace the methods
that your application calls.
Let's do this for the answer application
that I showed earlier.
So this is the source code for the
application.
And to simplify my demonstration, I'll
first put
a break point in the On Create method.
And now I'll start debugging the
application.
Now, as you can see, it stopped at the
break point.
And now, I want to start profiling.
So I'll open the DDMS View.
And click on the button that says
Start Profiling.
And now, I'll
return back to the debug view and
resume the application.
I'll let the program run for awhile and
now I'll return to the DDMS
view and press the same button as before,
this time to stop the profiling.
At this point, Traceview will process the
trace information and show it to me
graphically.
The Traceview display shows two panels.
One is a timeline view showing each
method, each method culls sequence and
duration,
The other is the profile view, which show
statistics and other information about
each culled method.
Let's look for our old friend Find Answer.
When I click on Find Answer in the profile
view I
can see where it was called up in the
Timeline view.
And now I can zoom in on the
timeline to see more information and
surrounding context.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And if I want to be more precise in my
profiling,
Android also allows me to insert
statements directly into the program.
That enable targeted tracing, and doing
this requires
that you set some permissions, however,
for your application.
And we haven't talked about permissions
yet, but
we'll talk about them in a later lesson.
And finally on my Mac if I Cmd+Click on
find answer in the Profile pane,
the clips will take me to the file
containing that method.
The last tool I'll talk about today is the
UI hierarchy view.
This tool allows you to analyze your
application's user interface and
understand how it's organized.
For example, let's look again at the Hello
Android application.
First, let's run the Hello Android
application.
And once it's up and running.
We'll go to the Menu bar and select
Window.
Then select Open Perspective.
Then select Hierarchy View.
Now if you don't see it, try selecting
Other and searching there instead.
Now once the Hierarchy Viewer starts,
we'll go
to the Window panel and double click the
entry
corresponding to the Hello Android
application, it's the
one that has the words, Hello Android in
it.
Double clicking on this entry will bring
up
a graphical representation of Hello
Android's user interface,
which like most user interfaces is
organized in a hierarchy.
For instance, there's an outermost
application
window, which holds the entire user
interface.
It contains two children, a title bar,
and the large rectangular body of the
application.
Each of these in turn contain further
elements.
Here, I'll click on the outermost window.
And I can in, inspect detailed information
about that window.
Such as its layout parameters which, for
example,
shows how big the window is in pixels.
The region occupied by each element is
shown here
in the layout view, in the bottom right
corner.
And the same information is also available
for the title bar, and
the same for the body, and the text to you
that it contains.
Now that's all for today's lesson on the
Android development environment.
Please join me next time when we'll
discuss the fundamental building blocks of
Android applications.
Thank you.