Hi, I'm Adam Porter and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
Another kind of resource is a Layout File.
Layout File specify what the user
interface for
some part of your application will look
like.
And again, these files are written in XML,
although
some tools will allow you to create the
layout visually.
And then those tools will generate the XML
for you.
In fact Eclipse will do that Layout files
are typically stored in the res/layout
directory of your application.
And you can access the layout in java
as r.layout.layout_name.
And you can access that layout in other
resource files as
@layout/layout_name.
Now just like string files whose
use depends on your default language.
Android allows you to create
multiple layout files.
And then Android can choose from those
files
at run time based on your device's
configuration.
Let's look at an example of that.
So let's look at the main .xml file that
is in the res/layout directory.
This file specifies that the layout is
composed of something called the relative
layout.
More on that when we talk about user
interfaces.
And inside the relative layout there's
another element called an edit
text, that's the box that you use for
entering the postal address.
There's also a button, that's the button
that was labeled show map.
Eclipse can also show what it thinks this
will all look like, at run time.
And you can see that by clicking on the
Graphical Layout tab.
Now
once you're there, you can also click on
the individual elements.
And Eclipse will show you more detailed
information about their layout properties.
MapLocation also has another file, also
called main.xml,
but this one is in the res/layout-land
directory.
If MapLocation is running with a device in
landscape mode this file
is used, instead of the one that we saw
before.
Now as you can see, this file uses the
same elements.
A relative layout, an edit text and a
button.
But I've changed their positioning
slightly, so that
the elements all appear on a single line.
Which I think looks better in landscape
mode.
And again, you can play around with
Eclipse to get
more details about the layout properties
of each individual element.
Now let's run the application.
The phone on the left is running in
portrait mode, so it uses the default
main.XML file.
The phone on the right however is running
in landscape mode, so it will use the
main.XML file that's in res/layout-land.
And as you can see, the elements are
actually
laid out differently depending on the
orientation of the device.
Now I've mentioned a few times now that
resources can
be accessed in Java as r dot something or
another.
Well, to do this, Android generates a
class called R
from your application and you can then
access the fields
of this R class to get to those strings
and
layouts and other resources that you
defined in the XML files.
Let's take a look at an, at an
actual R.JAVA file.
As I've said, this file is generated by
Android, so you shouldn't modify it.
You can see that the file defines the R
class, and this
R class contains another class called
Layout, which has a field called Main.
And that actually gives you a reference or
handle to the Main.XML file.
There's also an ID class, providing
handles to the relative layout, to the
edit text box and to the button defined in
the main.XML files.
In fact, if you go back and check the
main.XML
files now, you'll see that there are lines
that say Android:ID.
And that's where these fields and IDs come
from.
And finally, there's a class called string
which provides
handles for all the strings that we've
been talking about.
The next step in application development
is implementing your Java classes.
And this usually involves writing at least
one activity.
The entry point for activities is the
onCreate method.
So that's where you'll typically
initialize your application.
Let's look at the onCreate method in a bit
more detail.
In onCreate, you usually do the following
four things.
You restore saved application state.
You set the content view, which tells
android
what to display as the activity's user
interface.
You initialize specific elements of your
activity's user interface.
And last, you attach code to those user
interface
elements, so that specific actions will be
performed when
the users interact with these user
interface elements.
Let's see how these steps are implemented
in MapLocation.
So let's take a look at the MapLocation
source code.
Its all contained in a file
called MapLocation.java, in the
application's source
directory, now as you can see, this file
implements a class called MapLocation.
Which is a subclass of activity.
As an activity it has an onCreate method
where the application is initialized.
The first step of onCreate is to call
super.oncreate, passing saved instant
state as a parameter.
This saved instant is a something of type
bundle and
it's basically a data structure containing
any information that Android
might have saved from the last time the
activity was running.
We'll talk more about this next time when
we dive deeper into the activity class.
But for now, just be aware that onCreate
has to call super.onCreate, or you'll get
an error.
Next, there's a call to setContentView.
In this case, passing in the reference of
the layout file, for this application,
r.layout.main.
After that, there's some code that
acquires
references to individual UI elements in
the layout.
Such as the edit text box, which is stored
in a variable called,
adder text, and the button, which is
stored in a variable called button.
As you can see, these references are
acquired by calling
activity.findviewbyid and passing in the
id of the desired element.
And finally, there's some code that
defines what to
do when the user presses the show map
button.
This code implements the on click listener
interface, which has an on
click method that gets called whenever the
user clicks on this button.
And the code in that on click method first
gets
any text that the user has entered in the
address box.
Then it processes that text
to remove spaces and put it in a format
that Google Maps understands.
And then it starts the Google Map app,
Google Maps application, passing in this
modified address text.
And again, I'll explain what this code is
doing in more detail in later
lessons when we dive into the workings of
the activity class and the intent class.
And also, just to simplify things,
I have left out any error checking or
verification of the address string that
was input.
But of course in production code, you're
really going to want to do that.
The next step in creating Android
applications is to provide information
that allows Android's build tools to
create the application package or APK
and this information is written in an XML
file called androidmanifest.xml.
The AndroidManifest.xml file contains a
wide variety of packaging information.
Including the name of the application, and
a list
of the components that make up that
application.
It also includes other information, that
we'll discuss later in the course.
Things like the permissions that are
needed to run this application.
The hardware features, such as a camera
that this application
requires and the earliest platform version
on which this application runs.
Let's look at the androidmanifest.xml file
for MapLocation.
The androidmanifest.xml file is in the top
level directory of the application.
Let's open it now.
Inside you see that there is a manifest
tag telling
Android that this file contains the
packaging information that it needs.
There's a lot of other information in here
as
well but I'll just discuss a few pieces of
it.
One element we see here is the uses SDK
element.
This element includes an attribute, min
SDK
version, that specifies the minimum API
level for
this application.
And in this case, that level is ten,
which corresponds to one of the Android
2.3 releases.
This element also includes another
attribute, target STK version, which
specifies
the latest API level against which this
application has been tested.
In this case that's level 17 and
corresponds to a Android
4.2 release.
There's also an application element, that
specifies
things like the icon for this application.
And the label that's shown in the
application's title bar.
Inside the application element, there's an
activity element, that lists
the one activity, in this
case MapLocation, that comprises this
application.
And the last step is installing the
application on a
device or emulator in order to test and
debug it.
In an earlier lesson we saw how to do that
in Eclipse and you can
also do this from the command line, for
example, by issuing commands to the adb
tool.
So
that's all for application fundamentals,
please join me
next time when we will discuss the
activity class.
See you then.