Hi.
I'm Adam Porter.
And this is Programming Mobile
Applications For Android Handheld Systems.
In our last lesson, we talked about
the four fundamental components of Android
applications.
And they were activities, services,
broadcast receivers, and content
providers.
Today we're going to take a deeper look
at one of those components, the activity
class.
I'll start by presenting the activity
class itself.
Next, I'll discuss Android's task
backstack, which helps users
easily navigate back and forth among the
activities they use.
After that, I'll discuss the life cycle
of activities, how they're created,
executed and terminated.
And how
Android manages and communicates these
life cycle phases and changes.
To your applications.
After that I'll discuss the API's and
patterns
that you'll need to programatically to
start activities.
And finally I'll finish up with a, with a
discussion
of how Android activities handle device
and application configuration changes.
So I've said before,
activities are the primary class for
interacting with users.
They're designed to provide a visual
interface through
which the user can interact with the
application.
And by convention, activities should be
modular in the sense that each activity
should support a single focused thing that
the user can do with your application.
And individual things, like viewing an
email message or showing a login screen.
And if you follow this convention, then
you
end up creating applications by stringing
together multiple activities.
Each with a single purpose.
That the user then navigates through and
Android helps users
do this navigation in a couple of ways, by
supporting
the concept of tasks, by providing a task
backstack for
managing the specific activities through
which the user is navigating and
by ensuring that activities are properly
suspended and resumed
as they're pushed on and popped off the
task backstack.
In Android a task is simply a set of
related activities.These related
activities can, but don't have to be, part
of the same application.
So tasks can span multiple applications.
And most tasks start at the home screen.
So when a user launches an application
from the home screen a new task is
normally started.
And when a user hits the home button to
return back to
the home screen the current task is, is at
least temporarily closed.
The task backstack works as follows, when
an activity is launched it's
pushed onto the task backstack normally as
part of the current task.
When that activity is later destroyed, for
example, because the
user hit the back button, because the
activity terminated itself
programatically or even because Android
itself has decided to kill
that activity in order to reap its
resources, then the activity
is popped off the task backstack.
Let's take a look at how this process
works.
Now this graphic represents an activity
that's running on a device And
depicts the state of the task backstack
while the application is running.
The black pointer at the bottom indicates
the current snapshot.
Now when this application is first
launched it starts up activity
one, which is then pushed onto the top of
the task backstack as the root of the
current task.
Now as you can see, activity one has a
single button labeled Start Activity two.
So the idea here is that if the
user presses this button, Activity Two
will start.
So let's say now that the user presses the
Activity Two button.
At this point Activity One is suspended
and
its state will be captured so that it can
be restored later if the user returns back
to it.
Next, Activity Two begins and Activity Two
is pushed onto the task backstack.
Now similar to Activity One, Activity Two
has a single button.
Labeled Start Activity Three.
If the user presses this button, Activity
Three will start.
So let's say that the user now presses
the Start Activity Three button.
At this point Activity Two will be
suspended, Activity Three will
begin and Activity Three will be pushed on
to the task backstack.
Now, let's say that the user has had
enough of Activity Three and
hits the back button with the idea of
going back to Activity Two.
At this point Android kills Activity Three
and pops it off the task backstack.
Now because Activity Two is currently at
the top of
the task backstack, Android will unsuspend
or resume that activity.
Restoring it's state and bringing it back
into view on the device.
Now as we saw with the task backstack
examples.
Android activities come, and go, and come
again and go away for good.
The have a lifecycle.
And importantly for you as a developer
your
applications are not really in control of
this lifecycle.
Some lifecycle changes, for example,
depend on choices that the
user makes, like pressing the back button
or the home button.
Other lifecycle changes depend on Android
itself.
For example, if your device is running low
on memory,
Android can decide to kill activities that
are currently suspended.
And it will do that
knowing that it will need to recreate them
later if the user navigates back to them.
So let's talk a bit more about
the activity lifecycle and the particular
lifecycle changes.
That activities go through.
For example, once an activity is started,
it can be in a resumed or running state.
And, while it's in this state, the
activity
is visible and the user can interact with
it.
An activity can
also be paused.
For instance, when a new activity starts
to pop-up in front of it.
In this situation, the activity may still
be partially visible, but the user can't
interact
with it because the user will be
interacting with a new activity that's
starting up.
Prior to version 3.0, Android could
terminate
activities once they went into the paused
state.
Now finally, the activity can be stopped.
And when it is stopped that activity is
no longer visible and Android is free to
terminate.
And this is important to reiterate.
It can terminate stopped activities and it
does so knowing that
it might need to recreate them later if
the users navigate
back to them.
Now, your activities will often need to
behave
differently during different parts of
their life cycle.
For instance, if your activity is showing
an animation, but then
pops up a, partially transparent
dialogue-style
activity in front of it, what
you might want to pause the animation,
while the user responds to
the dialogue, and then restart the
animation, once that dialogue activity
finishes.
In order to support scenarios like this,
Android announces lifecycle changes to
your activity, by calling specific
lifecycle or template methods.
And some of these methods are shown here.
And each is named, as you can see, on
something rather.
OnCreate, when the activity's about to be
created.
OnStart, when the activity's about to
become visible.
All the way
to onDestroy when the activity's about to
be destroyed.
And if you want to take some specific
action when your activity changes
state,then you need to override one or
more of these methods in your activity.
So let's take a look at how
these different methods interrelate with
each other.
Now, this graphic depicts the orders in
which activity lifecycle methods can be
called.
And the important thing to remember here,
is that Android applications don't work
completely by themselves.
Instead, there's a clear back and
forth collaboration between your
application and Android.
And you have to understand the rules of
this collaboration.
If you want your Android applications to
function properly.
So let's imagine a simple application with
one activity.
That starts up,
waits for a moment, and then exits.
In this simple case when that application
is
launched, Android will call the activity's
On Create method.
Then, Android will call its onStart method
and then onResume, after which the
activity's
user interface will appear on the device's
screen and the user can interact with it.
After a minute or so our example
activity will begin to shut down.
And at this point Android will call that
activity onPause method.
Then onStop.
Then finally onDestroy.
And at this point the activity is
completely dead.
So, as you can see, the entire lifetime
of the activity runs from the start of
onCreate.
To the end of Ondestroy.
Now when this simple activity started it
wasn't visible on the screen.
At some point it became visible and at
some point
later it became invisible as it was
removed from the screen.
When activities are about to become
visible.
Android calls the onStart sometimes the
onRestart method.
When activities are about to become
invisible, Android calls the onStop
method.
And so you can think of the visible
lifetime of an activity as occurring
between the start of calls to onStart and
the end of calls to onStop.
And finally, while an activity is visible
on the screen, there are times when
the user can interact with it, and there
are times when he or she can't.
And, for example, this can happen when a
device goes to sleep.
In that case the user can't interact with
the
activity anymore even though it still is
the, the foreground activity.
So when activities are about to be ready
for user interaction Android calls the
onResume method.
When activities are about to stop being
able to
interact with the user, Android calls the
onPause method.
And so you can think of the visible and in
foreground lifetime
of an activity as occurring between the
start of calls to onResume and
the end of calls to onPause.
Let's walk through an, an example of this
based on
the map location application that we saw
in earlier lessons.
First, the user goes to home screen and
launches the map location application.
This causes the map location activity to
start up.
At which point Android calls Map
Location's onCreate method.
OnCreate initializes the activity.
And then Android continues by calling
onStart.
And at this point Map Location is visible
but not yet ready for user interaction.
And right now calls onResume.
After onResume completes Map Location
will soon be both visible and ready for
user interaction.
And at this point the user will normally
enter an address in the address box.
Once the address has been entered the user
will normally
press the show map button which will
launch Google Maps.
Now as Google Maps starts up it will have
its own initial activity,
that will go through its own lifecycle,
and receive its own lifecycle call backs.
Let's continue looking at what's going on
with the map location activity.
Now because Google maps is about to come
into the foreground and cover up map
location, the map location activity will
first receive
a call to its onPause method, and soon
after this.Map Location will no longer be
visible.
An Android will call its onStop method.
Now eventually Google Maps will appear on
the
screen, and the user can interact with it.
But at some point, the user will be done
with Google Maps and might,
for example, choose return back to map
location, for instance, to map a new
address.
So let's assume that the user now hits
the back button to return back to Map
Location.
At this point Map Location must be brought
back into the foreground.
So as Android does this it will first call
onRestart and then onStart.
And soon after this an application will
again be visible.
Next, Android will call Map Locations
onResume method, soon after which the
Map Location activity will be both visible
and ready for user interaction.
And finally when the user eventually loses
interest in application, he or she
might hit the back button again, in this
case to end the application.
At this point, Android will again go
through
the process of removing Map Location from
the screen.
It will first call onPause, then onStop,
and then
this time it will call onDestroy, before
completely terminating
the application.