Hi, I'm Adam Porter, and this is,
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
Today, we're going to talk about the four
fundamental
building blocks from which all Android
applications are built.
These building blocks are implemented as
Java classes.
And the first of these building blocks is
the activity class.
Now that's the main class that users see
when the run an application.
Activities are designed to provide a
graphical user interface, or a GUI, to the
user, and this enables users to give
and receive information to and from an
application.
The remaining three components work behind
the
scenes, so they don't have user
interfaces.
And these components include services
for supporting long running or in the
background operations.
Broadcast receivers that listen for and
respond to events that happen on a device.
And content providers which allow multiple
applications to store and share data.
Applications are typically created from
multiple collaborating components,
which Android starts up and runs as
necessary.
And each of these components serves
a different purpose in the Android
ecosystem.
And therefore, has it own entry point, and
its own APIs.
Let's take a look at each of these
components one at a time.
First, let's talk about the activity
class.
As I said earlier, this class is designed
to present a graphical user
interface to the user and to capture the
user's interaction through that interface.
As a general rule of thumb, an activity
should
support a single focused thing that the
user can do.
A single thing, like dialing a phone
number or
entering contact information for a single
person, and so on.
Now, of course, as device screens,
especially those
on tablets, get larger and larger, what we
mean by a single focus thing that the user
can do is, of course, bound to change.
Now, as an example of an activity, let's
take a look at the phone dialer
application.
Here I'll show you the phone application
running on an actual device.
You'll remember from earlier lessons
that the phone application can open a user
interface with multiple tabs.
One for a phone dialer, one for the call
log, and one for a contact list.
In Android 4.2, this application's source
code
is actually part of the contacts
application.
And it's written in a file called
dialtectsactivity.java.
Here I'll open that file.
As you can see the dial tects activity
class is a subclass of activity.
And the comments here
explain that this activity is supposed to
display a tab containing
the phone, the phone dialer, the call log
and the contacts list that I mentioned
earlier.
Let me pause here and give you a chance
to explore this source code for yourself.
The next component is the Service Class.
Unlike activity, services run in the
background.
So there's no need for services to have
user interfaces.
Instead, services have two main purposes.
One, they can perform long running
operations,
typically away from the main UI thread.
And two, they provide a way for
different processes to request operations
and share data.
Now for an example of a service, let's
take a look at the music application.
So here I'll show you the music
application running on a device.
As you can see the music application has a
number of different user interface screens
that show, for
example, your music Showing the songs
performed by a
single artist, letting you select one song
by that artist,
and finally letting you play that one
song.
Now if you start playing a song, however,
and then decide
to back up and see what other songs that
artist has.
Or if you want to do something totally
different, like check
your email, you probably don't want the
music to stop playing.
So Android handles this by using a service
to play the music.
Now here I'll go to the music application
and open
the MediaPlaybackService.java file.
As you can see, the media playback service
is a subclass, of service.
And the comments explain that this service
allows the music
to keep playing, even if the user switches
between different activities.
And again, let me pause here and give you
a chance to explore this source code for
yourself.
The next component is broadcast receiver.
Broadcast receiver's listen for and
respond to events.
And essentially they play the role
of the subscriber in the publish/subscribe
pattern.
In Android, events are represented by the
intent class.
Which we'll talk about more in later
classes.
Publishers create these intents and then
broadcast
them using a method like the context
classes, send broadcasts.
Now, once broadcasted, these intents are
then routed to the broadcast
receivers that have subscribed to, or
registered for, those specific intents.
At which point, they can respond to the
event.
Now, the messaging application is one
example
application that makes use of broadcast
receivers.
Let's take a look at that application.
So
let's imagine that somewhere out there in
the world, someone decides that they want
to send me an SMS message.
That SMS message will be created and
sent and will flow through the telephone
network and eventually arrive at my phone.
And when it does, Android will put a
notification icon in the
notification bar to let me know that an
SMS message has arrived
for me.
Now of course, you can't know exactly when
you're going to receive such a message.
So Android has some software that just
sits and waits for SMS messages to arrive.
And when they do, that software broadcasts
an SMS_received intent.
And there is another broadcast receiver
that is listening for that intent and
that broadcast receiver will eventually
receive the intent and will then start up
a service that will download and store the
incoming SMS message.
Now here I'll go to the MMS application
and open one of its broadcast receivers.
SMSreceiver.java.
As you can see, the SMS receiver class is
a subclass of broadcast receiver.
And the
comments explain that this broadcast
receiver
hands off the incoming SMS mesage to
a service which takes care of the
downloading and storage of the message.
Now once more, let's pause here and
explore the sorch-, the source code for
yourself.
The last component is content provider.
Content provider allows applications to
store and share data.
Content providers uses a database-style
interface
but they're more than just databases.
For example, content providers will handle
the low-level details of inter-process
communication.
So that applications running in separate
processes
can communicate and exchange data safely
and easily.
The browser application is one example of
an application that
uses content providers.
So here I'll start the browser
application.
If I click on the icon next to the address
bar, the browser opens a list of
bookmarks, or saved addresses,
for websites that I might want to access
quickly in the future.
When a user adds one of these bookmarks,
the browser application stores it in a
content provider.
Let's open the browser application source
code,
and take a look at the
browserprovider.java file.
As you can see, the browser provider is a
subclass of content provider.
And if we nose around a bit in the source
code, you can see some suggestions that
there's a database
table called bookmarks.
Which is used for storing the bookmarks
that the user adds.
Now I'll pause again here and let you
explore this source code for yourself.
In our last class we looked at the Hello
Android application.
That simple application involved just a
single activity.
Today, however, we're going to look at a
more complex application.
In this case comprised of two activities.
And, of course, once you know how to use
two activities, adding a
third, and a forth and so on, will just be
more of the same.
This application is called MapLocation and
one of its activities
allows the user to enter a postal address.
That activity also provides a button that
the user
can press, once he or she has entered that
address.
And pressing that button will then start
up a second activity, Google Maps,
that presents a map centered on the
address that the user just entered.
Let's take a look.
Now this
graphic depicts the process of writing and
building Android applications.
First, you create the source code and the
non-source code resources that make up
your application.
Next, tools compile your source code, and
prepare your resources.
The output of this step is an Android
package or APK which corresponds to your
application's executable.
Next the APK is digitally signed, to
identify you as its developer
and finally the APK is installed on a
device or emulator and run.
As a developer, your participation in the
build
process will usually involve the following
four steps.
Defining resources.
Implementing the application classes.
Packaging the application, and installing
and running the application.
In particular, for testing and debugging.
Step 1, is defining your application's
resources.
As I've said before, Android applications
are more than just source code.
They include non-source code entities as
well, things like
layout files, strings, images, menus,
animations and much more.
And managing resources separately from the
application has several benefits.
One of which is that you can easily alter
those resources
without having to change or recompile your
applications source code in any way.
One common resource type is strings.
In Android there are three types of string
resources.
Individual strings.
Arrays of strings and plurals.
Now I think strings and, and arrays of
strings are pretty self explanatory, let's
talk about plurals.
Plurals are basically string arrays
that can be used to choose specific
strings that are
associated with certain quantities, such
as one book, or two books.
And the strings are typically stored in an
XML file in the res/values directory of
your application.
And the format is a, an XML string
tag containing a name attribute and then
containing
the actual string itself.
And that actual string can include
formatting and styling information.
Things like HTML tags for example.
Finally, other resource files can refer to
the strings that you've defined as
@string/string_name.
In Java code, you can also access these
strings, but this time you do it as
R.string.string_name.
So, here we are again in Eclipse.
I've defined some strings for the Map
Location application.
Let's open the strings.xml file in the
res/values directory.
This file shows two strings,
show_map_string
with the value, show map.
And location_string,
with the value, enter location.
Now, I've also
defined a second string's.xml file.
This time for the Italian
language.
And it's in the res/values-it directory.
And that IT prefix in the directory name,
is what tells
Android that this is the string file for
the Italian language.
Now if we look at that file, we'll
see the same two strings, show_map_string
and location_string.
But this time their values are Italian
words rather than English words.
In the example I just showed, if your
default language
is Italian then location string will have
the value digita l'indirizzo.
Otherwise, it'll have the value enter
location.
Let's see that in action.
Now I'm going to run Map Location twice.
The phone on the left uses English as its
default language.
While the phone on the right uses Italian
as its default language.
Now as you can see, although both phones
are using the same exact source code, the
phone on the left, displays English
strings, while
the phone on the right, displays Italian
strings.